<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" ><generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="3.8.3">Jekyll</generator><link href="http://localhost:4000/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" /><link href="http://localhost:4000/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" /><updated>2019-01-19T15:06:41-05:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/</id><title type="html">Bill’s World</title><entry><title type="html">Using Cognitive Decentering to Become More Self-Aware</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/2018/07/25/cognitive-decentering.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Using Cognitive Decentering to Become More Self-Aware" /><published>2018-07-25T21:50:56-04:00</published><updated>2018-07-25T21:50:56-04:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/2018/07/25/cognitive-decentering</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/2018/07/25/cognitive-decentering.html">&lt;p&gt;Dr. &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.kent.edu/psychology/profile/david-m-fresco&quot;&gt;David Fresco&lt;/a&gt;, a professor of psychology and his colleauges at Kent State University have defined &lt;strong&gt;cognitive de-centering&lt;/strong&gt; as the &lt;em&gt;the ability to observe thoughts and feelings as only mental events, rather than as reality or truths about the self&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Thinking about this concept is fascinating to me. Imagine if we could examine our thoughts and feelings as mental events and not stuff we view as reality or stuff that can define us. It is like we hired Mr. Spock from Star Trek to help us understand what objective information and lessons can be learned from our thoughts and feelings when they are viewed as pieces of data. These pieces of data could be put together in order to give us objective evidence we might use to make better decisons or to become better communicators.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is not to say that emotion and how we feel and what we think is not important. On the contrary, how we feel and what we think is so important that we need to be able to step back and look at our thoughts and feelings objectively. The ability to cognitively de-center ourselves would minimize our tendencies to “read more” into a thought or a feeling. And by not “reading more” into our thoughts and feelings, we would be less likely to form erroneous perceptions about ourselves. In short, we would be able to get a truer picture of what we are thinking and what we are feeling in specific moments and situations.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>William (Bill) Schutz Jr.</name></author><summary type="html">Dr. David Fresco, a professor of psychology and his colleauges at Kent State University have defined cognitive de-centering as the the ability to observe thoughts and feelings as only mental events, rather than as reality or truths about the self.</summary></entry></feed>